Chapter 80. the nut.
If the sperm whale be physioogically a sphinx, to the phenologist, his brain
seems that geometrical circle which it is impossible to square.
In the full grown creature, the skull will measure at least 20 ft in length.
Unhinge the lower jaw, and the side view of this skull is as the side of a
moderately inclined plane resting throughout on a level base. But in life,
as we have elsewhere seen, this inclined plane is angularly filled up and almost
squared by the enormous super incumbent mass of the junk and sperm. At the high
end of the skull forms a crater to bed that part of the mass, while under the
long floor of this crater, in another cavity seldom exceeding 10 in in length
and as many in depth, reposes the mere handful of this monster's brain. The
brain is at least 20 ft from his apparent forehead in life. It is hidden
away behind its vast outworks, like the innermost citadel within the amplified
fortifications of Quebec. So like a choice casket is it secreted in him,
that I have known some whalemen who pereremptly deny that the sperm whale
has any other brain than that palpable semblance of one formed by the cubic
yards of his sperm magazine, lying in strange folds, courses, and convolutions
to their apprehensions. It seems more in keeping with the idea of his general
might to regard that mystic part of him as the seat of his intelligence.
It is plain then that phenologically the head of this Leviathan in the creature's
living intact state is an entire delusion. As for his true brain, you can
see no indications of it nor feel any.
The whale, like all things that are mighty, wears a false brow to the common world.
If you unload his skull of its heaps and then take a rear view of its
rear end, which is the high end, you will be struck by its resemblance to the
human skull, beheld in the same situation and from the same point of
view. Indeed, place this reversed skull scaled down to the human magnitude among
a plate of men's skulls, and you would involuntarily confound it with them, and
remarking the depressions on one part of its summit in phenological phrase, you
would say, "This man had no self-esteem and no veneration." And by those
negations considered along with the affirmative fact of his prodigious bulk
and power, you can best form to yourself the truest, though not the most
exhilarating conception of what the most exalted potency is.
But if from the comparative dimensions of the whale's proper brain, you deem it
incapable of being adequately charted, then I have another idea for you. If you
attentively regard almost any quadriped spine, you will be struck by the
resemblance of its vertebrae to a strung necklace of dwarfed skulls, all bearing
rudimental resemblance to the skull proper. It is a German conceit that the
vertebrae are absolutely undeveloped skulls. But the curious external
resemblance, I take it the Germans were not the first men to perceive. A foreign
friend once pointed it out to me in the skeleton of a foe he had slain, and with
the vertebrae of which he was inlaying in a sort of baso relievo, the beaked
prow of his canoe. Now I consider that the phronologists have omitted an
important thing in not pushing their investigations from the cerebellum
through the spinal canal, for I believe that much of a man's character will be
found be tokened in his backbone. I would rather feel your spine than your
skull, whoever you are. A thin joist of a spine never yet upheld a full and
noble soul. I rejoice in my spine, as in the firm, audacious staff of that flag
which I fling half out to the world.
Apply this spinal branch of phronology to the sperm whale. His cranial cavity
is continuous with the first neck vertebrae. And in that vertebrae, the
bottom of the spinal canal will measure 10 in across, being 8 in height, and of
a triangular figure with the base downwards. As it passes through the
remaining vertebrae, the canal tapers in size, but for a considerable distance
remains of large capacity. Now, of course, this canal is filled with much
the same strangely fibrous substance, the spinal cord, as the brain and
directly communicates with the brain.
And what is still more, for many feet after emerging from the brain's cavity,
the spinal cord remains of an undecreasing girth almost equal to that
of the brain. Under all these circumstances, would it be unreasonable
to survey and map out the whale's spine phenologically? For viewed in this
light, the wonderful comparative smallness of his brain proper is more
than compensated by the wonderful comparative magnitude of his spinal cord.
But leaving this hint to operate as it may with the phronologist, I would
merely assume the spinal theory for a moment in reference to the sperm whale's
hump. This august hump, if I mistake not, rises over one of the larger
vertebrae, and is therefore in some sort the outer convex mold of it. From its
relative situation, then I should call this high hump the organ of firmness or
indomitableness in the sperm whale, and that the great monster is indomitable,
you will yet have reason to know.